// cards-indonesian.js
deck = {
  language: "Indonesian",
  categories: {
    nouns: [
      // Pronouns
      { front: "saya; aku; gue", back: "I/me; my" },
      { front: "anda; kamu", back: "you; your" },
      { front: "dia", back: "him/her; his/her" },
      { front: "kita/kami", back: "us; our (incl. listener/excl. listener)" },
      { front: "kalian", back: "you (plural)" },
      { front: "meréka", back: "them; their" },

      // People; Family
      { front: "manusia", back: "human" },
      { front: "orang", back: "person" },
      { front: "orang-orang", back: "people" },
      { front: "laki-laki; tuan", back: "man; sir" },
      { front: "perempuan; nyonya/nona", back: "woman; madam/miss" },
      { front: "anak laki-laki", back: "boy; son" },
      { front: "anak perempuan", back: "girl; daughter" },

      { front: "keluarga", back: "family" },
      { front: "orang-tua", back: "parent" },
      { front: "bapak; pak", back: "father; mr/sir" },
      { front: "ibu; bu", back: "mother; mrs" },
      { front: "suami", back: "husband" },
      { front: "isteri", back: "wife" },
      { front: "pacar", back: "boyfriend; girlfriend" },
      { front: "anak; anak-anak", back: "child; children" },
      { front: "bayi", back: "baby" },
      { front: "saudara", back: "sibling" },
      { front: "mas; kakak (laki-laki)", back: "older brother" },
      { front: "adik laki-laki", back: "younger brother" },
      { front: "mbak; kakak (perempuan saya)", back: "older sister" },
      { front: "adik perempuan saya", back: "younger sister" },
      { front: "eyang", back: "grandparent" },
      { front: "kakek", back: "grandfather" },
      { front: "nének", back: "grandmother" },
      { front: "paman", back: "uncle" },
      { front: "bibi", back: "aunt" },
      { front: "sepupu", back: "cousin" },

      { front: "seseorang", back: "somebody" },
      { front: "tak seorangpun", back: "nobody" },
      { front: "semua orang", back: "everybody" },
      { front: "ternan; kawan", back: "friend" },
      { front: "tetangga", back: "neighbour" },
      { front: "lokal", back: "local" },

      { front: "nama", back: "name" },
      { front: "kepribadian", back: "personality" },
      { front: "umur", back: "age" },
      { front: "hubungan", back: "relationship; connection" },

      { front: "monster", back: "monster" },
      { front: "jago", back: "champion" },

      // School Related
      { front: "sekolah", back: "school; class" },
      { front: "sekolah dasar", back: "elementary school" },
      { front: "sekolah menengah", back: "middle school" },
      { front: "sekolah menengah atas", back: "high school" },
      { front: "universitas", back: "university" },
      { front: "guru", back: "teacher" },
      { front: "mahasiswa; pelajar", back: "student; learner" },

      { front: "uji", back: "test; exam" },
      { front: "buku", back: "book" },
      { front: "buku pelajaran", back: "textbook" },
      { front: "buku catatan", back: "notebook" },
      { front: "pénsil", back: "pencil" },
      { front: "péna", back: "pen" },
      { front: "kertas", back: "paper" },
      { front: "surat", back: "letter" },
      { front: "méja tulis", back: "desk" },
      { front: "kursi", back: "chair" },
      { front: "komputer", back: "computer" },

      { front: "studi", back: "studies" },
      { front: "dasar", back: "basic; base" },
      { front: "pertanyaan", back: "question" },
      { front: "kalimat", back: "sentence" },
      { front: "menjawab", back: "answer; response; reply" },
      { front: "penjelasan", back: "explanation" },
      { front: "penting", back: "important" },
      { front: "berarti", back: "meaning" },

      { front: "otodidak", back: "self-taught" },

      // Occupation
      { front: "kerja", back: "work" },
      { front: "polisi", back: "police" },
      { front: "dokter", back: "doctor" },

      // Home
      { front: "rumah", back: "home" },
      { front: "pintu", back: "door" },
      { front: "kamar", back: "room" },
      { front: "dapur", back: "kitchen" },
      { front: "kamar mandi", back: "bathroom" },
      { front: "toilet", back: "toilet" },
      { front: "cahaya", back: "light" },
      { front: "jendela", back: "window" },
      { front: "méja", back: "table" },
      { front: "cermin", back: "mirror" },
      { front: "sampah", back: "garbage" },

      // Objects
      { front: "benda", back: "thing; object" },
      { front: "sesuatu", back: "something" },
      { front: "tidak ada", back: "nothing" },

      { front: "tas", back: "bag" },
      { front: "dompet", back: "wallet" },
      { front: "télépon", back: "telephone" },
      { front: "uang", back: "money" },

      // Food
      { front: "makanan", back: "food" },
      { front: "daging", back: "meat" },
      { front: "makanan laut", back: "seafood" },
      { front: "sayur", back: "vegetables" },
      { front: "buah", back: "fruit" },
      { front: "permen", back: "candy" },
      { front: "kacang", back: "nuts" },

      { front: "cabe", back: "pepper (chili)" },
      { front: "lobak", back: "daikon; radish" },

      { front: "kécap", back: "soy sauce" },
      { front: "gula", back: "sugar" },
      { front: "garam", back: "salt" },
      { front: "merica", back: "pepper" },
      { front: "saos", back: "sauce" },
      { front: "saos tomat", back: "ketchup; tomato sauce" },

      // Animal
      { front: "satwa", back: "animal" },
      { front: "burung", back: "bird" },
      { front: "anjing", back: "dog" },
      { front: "kucing", back: "cat" },
      { front: "ayam", back: "chicken" },
      { front: "bébék", back: "duck" },
      { front: "sapi", back: "cow" },
      { front: "babi", back: "pig" },
      { front: "kuda", back: "horse" },
      { front: "domba", back: "sheep; lamb" },
      { front: "tikus", back: "rat" },

      { front: "ikan", back: "fish" },
      { front: "udang besar", back: "lobster" },
      { front: "udang", back: "shrimp" },
      { front: "kepiting", back: "crab" },
      { front: "tiram", back: "oyster" },
      { front: "cumi-cumi; sotong", back: "squid" },
      { front: "penyu; kura-kura", back: "turtle; tortoise" },

      { front: "monyet", back: "monkey" },
      { front: "singa", back: "lion" },
      { front: "harimau", back: "tiger" },
      { front: "serigala", back: "wolf" },
      { front: "beruang", back: "bear" },
      { front: "ular", back: "snake" },
      { front: "naga", back: "dragon" },
      { front: "anjing laut", back: "seal" },

      // Time
      { front: "waktu", back: "time" },
      { front: "jam", back: "hour; o’clock" },
      { front: "menit", back: "minute" },
      { front: "kedua", back: "second" },
      { front: "pagi", back: "morning" },
      { front: "soré", back: "afternoon" },
      { front: "malam", back: "evening" },
      { front: "tidur", back: "night" },

      { front: "hari", back: "day" },
      { front: "hari ini", back: "today" },
      { front: "kemarin", back: "yesterday" },
      { front: "bésok", back: "tomorrow" },

      { front: "minggu", back: "week" },
      { front: "minggu ini", back: "this week" },
      { front: "minggu lalu", back: "last week" },
      { front: "minggu depan", back: "next week" },
      { front: "akhir pekan", back: "weekend" },

      { front: "bulan", back: "month" },
      { front: "bulan ini", back: "this month" },
      { front: "bulan lalu", back: "last month" },
      { front: "bulan depan", back: "next month" },

      { front: "tahun", back: "year" },
      { front: "tahun ini", back: "this year" },
      { front: "tahun lalu", back: "last year" },
      { front: "tahun depan", back: "next year" },

      { front: "sekarang", back: "now" },
      { front: "sebelum", back: "before" },
      { front: "sesudah", back: "after" },
      { front: "nanti", back: "later" },
      { front: "segera", back: "soon" },

      { front: "januari", back: "January" },
      { front: "fébruari", back: "February" },
      { front: "maret", back: "March" },
      { front: "april", back: "April" },
      { front: "méi", back: "May" },
      { front: "juni", back: "June" },
      { front: "juli", back: "July" },
      { front: "agustus", back: "August" },
      { front: "séptémber", back: "September" },
      { front: "oktober", back: "October" },
      { front: "nopember", back: "November" },
      { front: "désémber", back: "December" },

      { front: "musim", back: "season" },
      { front: "musim panas", back: "summer" },
      { front: "musim gugur", back: "fall" },
      { front: "musim dingin", back: "winter" },
      { front: "musim semi", back: "spring" },

      // Body Parts (add if you want)

      // Clothing (add if you want)

      // Transportation
      { front: "sepéda", back: "bicycle" },
      { front: "mobil", back: "car; automobile" },
      { front: "bis", back: "bus" },
      { front: "taksi", back: "taxi" },
      { front: "keréta api", back: "train" },
      { front: "pesawat", back: "airplane" },
      { front: "perahu", back: "boat" },

      // Countries & Language
      { front: "dunia", back: "world" },
      { front: "benua", back: "continent" },
      { front: "negara", back: "country" },
      { front: "spanyol", back: "Spain" },
      { front: "kanada", back: "Canada" },
      { front: "amerika serikat", back: "USA" },
      { front: "jepang", back: "Japan" },
      { front: "filipina", back: "Philippines" },
      { front: "perancis", back: "France" },
      { front: "italia", back: "Italy" },
      { front: "indonesia", back: "Indonesia" },
      { front: "islandia", back: "Iceland" },
      { front: "cina; tionghoa", back: "China" },
      { front: "korea", back: "Korea" },

      { front: "bahasa", back: "Language" },
      { front: "bahasa inggris", back: "English" },

      { front: "kata", back: "word" },
      { front: "nomor", back: "number" },
      { front: "kosakata", back: "vocabulary" },
      { front: "tata bahasa", back: "grammar" },
      { front: "pengucapan", back: "pronunciation" },
      { front: "fasih", back: "fluent" },
      { front: "percakapan", back: "conversation" },
      { front: "subjek", back: "subject" },

      // Media and Entertainment (add if you want)

      // Places (add if you want)

      // Direction
      { front: "di sini", back: "here" },
      { front: "di sana; di situ", back: "there" },
      { front: "di dalam", back: "inside" },
      { front: "di luar", back: "outside" },
      { front: "di atas", back: "above; upstairs" },
      { front: "di bawah", back: "below; downstairs" },
      { front: "di depan", back: "in front" },
      { front: "di belakang", back: "behind" },
      { front: "kanan", back: "right" },
      { front: "kiri", back: "left" },
      { front: "utara", back: "north" },
      { front: "selatan", back: "south" },
      { front: "timur", back: "east" },
      { front: "barat", back: "west" },

      // Abstract
      { front: "tapi boong", back: "lie" },
      { front: "spesial; istimewa", back: "special" },

      // Question Words
      { front: "siapa", back: "who" },
      { front: "apa", back: "what" },
      { front: "di mana", back: "where" },
      { front: "kapan", back: "when" },
      { front: "kenapa", back: "why" },
      { front: "bagaimana", back: "how" },
      { front: "berapa", back: "how much/many" },
      { front: "berapa lama", back: "how long" },
      { front: "yang mana", back: "which (one)" }
    ],
        adjectives: [
      // Colour
      { front: "warna", back: "colour" },
      { front: "biru", back: "blue" },
      { front: "merah", back: "red" },
      { front: "kuning", back: "yellow" },
      { front: "hijau", back: "green" },
      { front: "jingga", back: "orange" },
      { front: "ungu", back: "purple" },
      { front: "merah muda", back: "pink" },
      { front: "coklat", back: "brown" },
      { front: "putih", back: "white" },
      { front: "hitam", back: "black" },
      { front: "abu-abu", back: "grey" },

      // Size and Shape
      { front: "besar", back: "big" },
      { front: "kecil", back: "small" },
      { front: "tinggi", back: "tall" },
      { front: "pendek", back: "short" },
      { front: "lebar", back: "wide" },
      { front: "sempit", back: "narrow" },
      { front: "gendut", back: "fat" },
      { front: "kurus", back: "thin" },
      { front: "panjang", back: "long" },

      // Feelings
      { front: "senang", back: "happy" },
      { front: "sedih", back: "sad" },
      { front: "marah", back: "angry" },
      { front: "tenang", back: "calm" },
      { front: "sadar", back: "awake" },
      { front: "lelah", back: "tired" },
      { front: "menakutkan", back: "scary" },

      // Qualities and Appearance
      { front: "baik", back: "good" },
      { front: "buruk", back: "bad" },
      { front: "cantik", back: "beautiful; pretty" },
      { front: "imut", back: "cute" },
      { front: "tampan", back: "handsome" },
      { front: "keren", back: "cool" },
      { front: "jelek", back: "ugly" },
      { front: "cerdas / pintar", back: "intelligent; smart" },
      { front: "bodoh", back: "stupid" },
      { front: "ramah", back: "kind; friendly" },
      { front: "kasar", back: "rude" },
      { front: "kaya / sultan", back: "rich" },
      { front: "miskin", back: "poor" },
      { front: "kuat", back: "strong" },
      { front: "lemah", back: "weak" },
      { front: "keras", back: "loud" },
      { front: "diam", back: "quiet" },
      { front: "pemula", back: "beginner" },
      { front: "ahli", back: "expert; skilled" },
      { front: "berguna", back: "useful" },
      { front: "tidak berguna", back: "useless" },

      // Condition
      { front: "terbaik / lebih baik", back: "best; better" },
      { front: "terburuk / lebih buruk", back: "worst; worse" },
      { front: "normal", back: "normal" },
      { front: "umum", back: "common" },
      { front: "aneh", back: "weird" },
      { front: "mudah", back: "easy" },
      { front: "sulit", back: "difficult" },
      { front: "sederhana", back: "simple" },
      { front: "rumit", back: "complicated" },

      // Age & Time
      { front: "baru", back: "new" },
      { front: "lama", back: "old (thing)" },
      { front: "muda", back: "young" },
      { front: "tua", back: "old (person)" },

      // Temperature / Wetness
      { front: "panas", back: "hot" },
      { front: "dingin", back: "cold" },
      { front: "kering", back: "dry" },
      { front: "basah", back: "wet" },

      // Fun & Interest
      { front: "menarik", back: "interesting" },
      { front: "lucu", back: "funny" },
      { front: "menghibur", back: "fun; entertaining" },
      { front: "membosankan", back: "boring" },

      // Comparison
      { front: "sama", back: "same" },
      { front: "berbeda", back: "different" },
      { front: "lainnya", back: "other" },

      // Quantity
      { front: "banyak", back: "a lot; many" },
      { front: "sedikit", back: "little (not much); few" },
      { front: "penuh", back: "full" },
      { front: "kosong", back: "empty" },
      { front: "mahal", back: "expensive" },
      { front: "murah", back: "cheap" },
      { front: "gratis", back: "free" },

      // Speed & Time
      { front: "cepat", back: "fast" },
      { front: "lambat", back: "slow" },
      { front: "sibuk", back: "busy" },
      { front: "bebas / tersedia", back: "free (time); available" },
      { front: "pagi", back: "early" },
      { front: "telat", back: "late" },

      // Taste
      { front: "enak / sedang / lezat", back: "delicious; tasty" },
      { front: "maknyus", back: "super delicious" },
      { front: "tidak enak / mengerikan", back: "untasty; horrible" },
      { front: "manis", back: "sweet; cute (sweet)" },
      { front: "pedas", back: "spicy" },
      { front: "pahit", back: "bitter" },
      { front: "kecut", back: "sour" },
      { front: "asin", back: "salty" },
      { front: "segar", back: "fresh" },
      { front: "mentah", back: "raw" }
    ],
    verbs: [
      { front: "Ada", back: "to be; have; exist" },
      { front: "Punya", back: "to have; own" },
      { front: "Jadi", back: "to become" },
      { front: "Buat", back: "to do; make" },
      { front: "Bisa", back: "to be able to; can" },
      { front: "Tahu", back: "to know (information)" },
      { front: "Kenal", back: "to know (someone)" },
      { front: "Ahami", back: "to understand" },
      { front: "Datang", back: "to come; arrive" },
      { front: "Pergi", back: "to go" },
      { front: "Pulang", back: "to go back (home)" },
      { front: "Bicara", back: "to speak/talk" },
      { front: "Dengar", back: "to listen to; hear" },
      { front: "Lihat", back: "to see" },
      { front: "Nonton", back: "to watch" },
      { front: "Mau", back: "to want; to desire" },
      { front: "Ingin", back: "to want; to desire" },
      { front: "Perlu", back: "to need" },
      { front: "Suka", back: "to like" },
      { front: "Sayang", back: "to love" },
      { front: "Cinta", back: "to love" },
      { front: "Menulis", back: "to write" },
      { front: "Membaca", back: "to read" },
      { front: "Belajar", back: "to study" },
      { front: "Pelajari", back: "to learn" },
      { front: "Mengajar", back: "to teach" },
      { front: "Ingat", back: "to remember" },
      { front: "Lupa", back: "to forget" },
      { front: "Makan", back: "to eat" },
      { front: "Minum", back: "to drink" },
      { front: "Masak", back: "to cook" },
      { front: "Bepergian", back: "to travel" },
      { front: "Bekerja", back: "to work" },
      { front: "Rasa", back: "to feel" },
      { front: "Kasih", back: "to give" },
      { front: "Terima", back: "to receive" },
      { front: "Ambil", back: "to take" },
      { front: "Main", back: "to play" },
      { front: "Tawa", back: "to laugh" },
      { front: "Coba", back: "to try" },
      { front: "Buka", back: "to open" },
      { front: "Tutup", back: "to close" },
      { front: "Mulai", back: "to begin" },
      { front: "Akhir", back: "to end" },
      { front: "Berhenti", back: "to stop" },
      { front: "Dapat", back: "to get; reach; attain" },
      { front: "Masuk", back: "to go in; enter" },
      { front: "Keluar", back: "to go out; exit" },
      { front: "Duduk", back: "to sit" },
      { front: "Lari", back: "to run" },
      { front: "Jalan", back: "to walk; travel" },
      { front: "Beli", back: "to buy" },
      { front: "Jual", back: "to sell" },
      { front: "Taruh", back: "to put; place" },
      { front: "Bawa", back: "to carry" },
      { front: "Cari", back: "to look for; seek" },
      { front: "Tidur", back: "to sleep" },
      { front: "Pakai", back: "to use; wear" },
      { front: "Lahir", back: "to be born" },
      { front: "Nikah", back: "to marry" },
      { front: "Naik", back: "to ride" },
      { front: "Kenjungi", back: "to visit" },
      { front: "Menélepon", back: "to call; telephone" },
      { front: "Bertemu", back: "to meet" }
    ],
    adverbs: [
      // Conjunctions
      { front: "dan", back: "and" },
      { front: "atau", back: "or" },
      { front: "tapi / tetapi", back: "but; but (unfortunately)" },
      { front: "akan tetapi", back: "but (formal)" },
      { front: "karena", back: "because" },
      { front: "jika / jika (maka)", back: "if; if (then)" },
      { front: "begini / begitu", back: "thus; so" },
      { front: "jadi", back: "so" },
      { front: "sehingga", back: "as a result" },
      { front: "kemudian", back: "then; afterwards" },
      { front: "untuk", back: "in order to; for" },
      { front: "misalnya", back: "for example" },
      { front: "sebenarnya", back: "actually; really" },
      { front: "juga", back: "also" },
      { front: "kedua-duanya", back: "both" },

      // Degree
      { front: "sangat / banget / sekali", back: "very" },
      { front: "terlalu", back: "too" },
      { front: "paling / ter-", back: "most; -est" },

      // Frequency
      { front: "selalu", back: "always" },
      { front: "sering", back: "often" },
      { front: "kadang-kadang", back: "sometimes" },
      { front: "jarang", back: "rarely" },
      { front: "tidak pernah", back: "never" },
      { front: "baru-baru ini", back: "recently" },
      { front: "sekitar / kira-kira", back: "about; approximately" },
      { front: "selama", back: "during" },
      { front: "sudah / telah", back: "already" },
      { front: "belum", back: "not yet" },

      // Level of Certainty
      { front: "tentu saja / iya dong", back: "of course" },
      { front: "mungkin", back: "maybe" },

      // Amount
      { front: "semua (semuanya)", back: "all (everything)" },
      { front: "tidak ada", back: "nothing" },
      { front: "lebih", back: "more" },
      { front: "kurang", back: "less" },

      // Other
      { front: "lagi", back: "again" },
      { front: "masih / tetap", back: "still" },
      { front: "sejak", back: "since" },
      { front: "hanya", back: "only" },
      { front: "dengan / pakai", back: "with; with (to use)" },
      { front: "hampir", back: "almost" },
      { front: "di", back: "in" },
      { front: "dari", back: "from" },
      { front: "ke", back: "to" }
    ]
  }
};
